measuring today is composable view some
patterns and a tip that might be able to
help you write a better compostable
my name is anthony fu and i'm view
courting member and also a member of it
i have created several projects like
i really love open source and now i'm
you can find me on github and twitter
i start i want to give a thanks to all
my sponsors to support my work and
make make all this happen if you enjoy
as well you can find the links to
it's all started with me made this
which is a collection of view composable
initially i was making this to share
that i wrote with view composition api
till now it grows much bigger with the
we are now in organizations on github
team members and eight add-on package
we also have more than 100 utilities in
core package that worked for both view 2
i'm really appreciative for all the
in the osan community in today's talk
i will share with you what i have
learned during developing view use and
use it to make apps in composition api
by the way please note today's talk will
which i would assume you already have a
the view composition api is but don't
i believe you are you will get some
basic image of the methodology and you
can find the slides and transcripts
well let's start with riff and reactive
i bet many of you have wondered the
difference between them and which one
you can sing riffs as variables and the
objects when you do the assignments one
the other one well the other one is
while the usage of them can really
depends on what you're gonna use them
but if we really need to pick one from
them let's say go with riff whenever you
we're sure if you will need to use dot
value to assessing and assigning values
but this also gives you more explicit
when you are when you are tracking and
triggering the reactivity system
as you can see the example here i
by accidentally assigning a value into
into a roof so here i can change the
but on the other hand with with reactive
you you cannot tell you can you cannot
tell the difference between a plane
reactive object without looking into the
which could sometimes make the debugging
also note in reactive objects there are
cabinets you need to take care about
you you can do the structure without two
otherwise they will lose the reactivity
and you will also need to wrap with the
when using with watch and so on where
rift does not have such limitations
when using with riffs a big obstacle
the annoying dot value but actually in
you can omit it and make your code looks
the watch function accepts a riff as a
as a watch source directly and will
new value of the of the riff in the
so in these cases there is no dot value
the other one is the natural of view in
templates all the riffs are also
and whenever you feel like tobacco works
you can pass a riff into a reactive
and when you assess the properties
the ribs automatically for you change to
the original riff will also reflect to
unreef is another composition api i
as the name unreal sums is kind of
while the ray function takes the value
unreef takes a riff and returns its
the interesting part of it is that if
you pass the plan value to the wrong
it will return the value as is to you
you can see the implementation is
this is not a big feature but a good tip
to unify your logic which i will show
so that's a tip for using riff and
reactive here i'd like to share
with you some patterns of writing
so what is composable functions it's
actually kind of hard to give a purple
but i i'd like to think think them as
a set of irreusable logic and make you
to make your code better organized and
here is an example the use dark function
in view use is provided as a simple
toggle for enable and disable dark mode
there are actually two variables
preference and the other one is user's
as you can see in the this code snippets
composable functions use preferred dock
storage they will return two riffs
and that's reflecting to their states
detailed things like monitoring media
query changes and the timing to read and
and all i need to do is to logically
into a single riff so you can see
here you can see the phone code and or
use it in view use with the links below
okay and the first methodology i want to
unlike hooks in react that will runs on
the apt the setup function in view only
component initializations to construct
between your state and the logic
you can think the equations of in
where the left hand side is always equal
here is an example that we have z equal
x squared plus y squared where y x and y
and z is a controllable it's a
controlled variables relying on x and
y whenever i changed any of them
there will be updated accordingly which
in spreadsheets so in composable
we can sync arguments as input and
the returns as the output the output
on input changes automatically
i will talk with you this with an
another aspect is to do one thing at a
as these are basically the same as you
any code no need for me to spend too
but they are basically this here note
it's also important to have a consistent
like prefix with use or create and so on
to make the compostable function
distinguishable from other functions
all right let's start with our first
here here we have a plan functions which
arguments a and b you can also see the
and then we can make this function
and the returns are computable compute
their sum then we can pass the ribs into
as we normally would the difference here
the return value is also a riff but it
will also it will always up to date with
a and b and remember the unreal function
we can actually make these functions
by accepting both riffs and plane values
and use unref to get their values
we can also make the addition possible
here is a simple typescript type helper
called maybe riff that we have used a
it's basically a union of type generic t
and derivative in this example we have a
function use time ago that's a separate
normally if you want to accept riffs you
again english versions with this helpers
you can make the code shorter and more
a cool point is that it works great with
it can invert correct types for maybe
you can sync your functions like there
go they should have many different
ways of composing them for different
here we take use title function from
basically when you call it you you will
get a special riff that binds into the
title whenever you change the riffs
the page's title will also be updated
similarly when the pages when when the
pages title changes externally
the change will also be reflect on the
looks good right but it creates a new
to make it more flexible we can actually
here you can see i construct a computed
when i change the source riff the
revalued and so as the page's title
you must be wonder how this could be
let's take a look at the simplified
so there is only two there is actually
two statements one is riff and the other
we unify the riffs from the user or
and on the second line it watches the
to the riff and the sync up with page
maybe it's a little bit hard to catch up
in the first line let me explain it a
here we utilize the interesting
similar to on riff roof also check
value is the roof or not if you pass a
leave it as is since there is already a
there is no need to make another
this could be extremely useful in
takes maybe read as argument types
let's do a quick summary so far we can
use maybe rift in arguments to make the
and use three functions when you want to
and use unreal functions when you want
both of them are universal and there is
another pattern today is to use object
we will need to return multiple data
entries in a composable function
consider return a object composable
in this way user can have full features
object destructure the under the
values are also ripped so the reactive
and the user user can also rename it or
take only partial of it as they want
on the other hand is also flexible
enough when users want to use it as a
simply simply wrap it with a reactive
the riff will get unwrapped with as a
can get benefits from both riff and the
since we are constructing connections
we can actually make async functions to
sync by building the connection first
before it resolve let's say we want to
using the fetch api normally we would
await the request being responsed and
the payload being passed before we can
with composition api we can actually
make the data as a riff of new
then be fulfilled later this can make
your app take time to handle other stuff
while waiting for the data to be fetched
the idea is similar to swr but with much
the implementation can be simple down as
all we have to do is to assign value to
riffs when the promise gets resolved
in real world it might need some flags
to show the current state of the request
where you can find the phone calls in
auto and computed in view will stop stop
along with the components are mounting
to following the the same pattern for
your custom composable functions
by calling the unmounted hooks inside
you can schedule the effect cleanup
for example it's common to use add event
register the handler of dom events
when you finish the usage it would also
remove event listener in this case we
have a function use event listener
itself along with the components so you
don't need to worry about it anymore
while side effects auto cleanup is nice
have better controls over when to do
i drafted an rfc proposing a new api
called effect scope to collect those
effects into a single instance
that you can stop them together at any
this is likely to be implemented and
check out for more details if it gets in
we have a set of new api called provider
it's basically for sharing some context
for components choosing to consume and
there are two separate functions which
means typescript can actually infer
the type for each context automatically
but here we have a solution for that
view provided a type helper called
injection key where you can define
where you can define a symbol that
and it will hinge provided and inject to
auto completion and type checking
for example here i define an interface
which contains two properties and i
the injection type in usage i can use
provide the data with key as you can see
i can i got it i gotta type arrows that
so i can catch up the air arrow right
and in current components we can use
injection functions with the key as well
you can see the correctly inferred types
sharing state is actually quite simple
riffs and reactive states in a
import them in your components since
they are using the same instance
the state will be just in sync but
this is actually not server side
in server rendering your server will
on each request where the approach will
will keep the state persistent across
and normally it's not what we would
let's see if we can make a solution for
for it to work with server-side
by you by using provider and inject to
the app contacts which means it will
every time we're in the server doing the
you can you can see here i have two
use create state will return the view
the state to the apps while you use my
injection nets using the same key
in usage we can create the state in the
main entries and the passage to app.use
and you can use the hooks to use my
stats everywhere in your components
if you ever tried view router v4
it's actually using the similar similar
to do that like create router and use
one last tip i like to share is a
it's actually a simple wrap to component
pops and emits but it's actually a life
we can take that we can take a look at
you can see we use a writable computed
we forward the the value of pops to it
and when writing we image out the
so you can use it you can use it as a
even more we can actually bind into the
elements v remodels very easily
that's all the tips and the patterns i
as you may think those are for view
three only but actually they also apply
in case you don't know that if you're
still on view too but want to get
started with the competition api
here we offer an official plugin that's
enabled competition api for your view 2
we also announced our plans for view 2.7
view 2.7 will be the last micro version
with the long time support for existing
iep ie11 support we will backport view
2.7 and migrate the viewer composition
if you are library officers that belong
view 2 and 3 at the same code base
you can try viewdemi which is out the
difference between view 2 and 3
and by auto detecting users environment
and that's all for today here is a quick
due to the time limitations it says
shame that i cannot share all i have
as view competition api is still fairly
new i believe there are more patterns
and the better practice for us to fund
to get more information to check out the
viewus.org on github and its awesome
and follow us on twitter at view use to
keep up to date with the news and the
slides of this toy can be found on my
antfu.me thank you for listening
let's see in the qa section bye